<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version
    2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required by
    applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
    License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR
    CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for
    the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the
    License.
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:id="cayenne-mapping-structure">
    <title>Cayenne Mapping Structure</title>
    <section xml:id="cayenne-project">
        <title>Cayenne Project</title>
        <para>A Cayenne project is an XML representation of a model connecting database schema with
            Java classes. A project is normally created and manipulated via CayenneModeler GUI and
            then used to initialize Cayenne runtime. A project is made of one or more files. There's
            always a root project descriptor file in any valid project. It is normally called
                <code>cayenne-xyz.xml</code>, where "xyz" is the name of the project.</para>
        <para>Project descriptor can reference DataMap files, one per DataMap. DataMap files are
            normally called <code>xyz.map.xml</code>, where "xyz" is the name of the DataMap. For
            legacy reasons this naming convention is different from the convention for the root
            project descriptor above, and we may align it in the future versions. Here is how a
            typical project might look on the file
            system:<programlisting>~: ls -l
total 24
-rw-r--r--  1 cayenne  staff  491 Jan 28 18:25 cayenne-project.xml
-rw-r--r--  1 cayenne  staff  313 Jan 28 18:25 datamap.map.xml</programlisting></para>
        <para>DataMap are referenced by name in the root
            descriptor:<programlisting>&lt;map name="datamap"/></programlisting></para>
        <para>Map files are resolved by Cayenne by appending <code>.map.xml</code>" extension to the
            map name, and resolving the resulting string relative to the root descriptor URI. The
            following sections discuss varios ORM model objects, without regards to their XML
            representation. XML format details are really unimportant to the Cayenne users.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="datamap">
        <title>DataMap</title>
        <para>DataMap is a container of persistent entities and other object-relational metadata.
            DataMap provides developers with a scope to organize their entities, but it does not
            provide a namespace for entities. In fact all DataMaps present in runtime are combined
            in a single namespace. Each DataMap must be associated with a DataNode. This is how
            Cayenne knows which database to use when running a query.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="datanode">
        <title>DataNode</title>
        <para>DataNode is model of a database. It is actually pretty simple. It has an arbitrary
            user-provided name and information needed to create or locate a JDBC DataSource. Most
            projects only have one DataNode, though there may be any number of nodes if
            needed.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbentity">
        <title>DbEntity</title>
        <para>DbEntity is a model of a single DB table or view. DbEntity is made of DbAttributes
            that correspond to columns, and DbRelationships that map PK/FK pairs. DbRelationships
            are not strictly tied to FK constraints in DB, and should be mapped for all logical
            "relationships" between the tables.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="objentity">
        <title>ObjEntity</title>
        <para>ObjEntity is a model of a single persistent Java class. ObjEntity is made of
            ObjAttributes and ObjRelationships. Both correspond to entity class properties. However
            ObjAttributes represent "simple" properties (normally things like String, numbers,
            dates, etc.), while ObjRelationships correspond to properties that have a type of
            another entity. </para>
        <para>ObjEntity maps to one or more DbEntities. There's always one "root" DbEntity for each
            ObjEntity. ObjAttribiute maps to a DbAttribute or an Embeddable. Most often mapped
            DbAttribute is from the root DbEntity. Sometimes mapping is done to a DbAttribute from
            another DbEntity somehow related to the root DbEntity. Such ObjAttribute is called
            "flattened". Similarly ObjRelationship maps either to a single DbRelationship, or to a
            chain of DbRelationships ("flattened" ObjRelationship).</para>
        <para>ObjEntities may also contain mapping of their lifecycle callback methods.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="embeddable">
        <title>Embeddable</title>
        <para>Embeddable is a model of a Java class that acts as a single attribute of an ObjEntity,
            but maps to multiple columns in the database.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="procedure">
        <title>Procedure</title>
        <para>A model of a stored procedure in the database.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="query">
        <title>Query</title>
        <para>A model of a query. Cayenne allows queries to be mapped in Cayenne project, or created
            in the code. Depending on the circumstances the users may take one or the other
            approach.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
