<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version
	2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
	with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required by
	applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR
	CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for
	the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the
	License.
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:id="introduction-to-rop">
    <title>Introduction to ROP</title>
    <section xml:id="what-is-rop">
        <title>What is ROP</title>
		<para>"Remote Object Persistence" is a low-overhead web services-based technology that
			provides lightweight object persistence and query functionality to 'remote'
			applications. In other words it provides familiar Cayenne API to applications that do
			not have direct access to the database. Instead such applications would access Cayenne
			Web Service (CWS). A single abstract data model (expressed as Cayenne XML DataMap) is
			used on the server and on the client, while execution logic can be partitioned between
			the tiers.The following picture compares a regular Cayenne web application and a rich
			client application that uses remote object persistence technology:</para>
    	<para><inlinemediaobject>
    		<imageobject>
    			<imagedata fileref="images/remote-object-persistence.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
    		</imageobject>
    	</inlinemediaobject></para>
		<para>Persistence stack above consists of the following parts:<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>ORM Tier: a server-side Cayenne Java application that directly connects to
						the database via JDBC.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>CWS (Cayenne Web Service): A wrapper around an ORM tier that makes it
						accessible to remote CWS clients.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Remote Tier (aka Client Tier): A Java application that has no direct DB
						connection and persists its objects by connecting to remote Cayenne Web
						Service (CWS). Note that CWS Client doesn't have to be a desktop
						application. It can be another server-side application. The word "client"
						means a client of Cayenne Web Service.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="main-features">
        <title>Main Features</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			
					<listitem>
						<para>Unified approach to lightweight object persistence across multiple
							tiers of a distributed system.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Same abstract object model on the server and on the client.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Client can "bootstrap" from the server by dynamically loading
							persistence metadata.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>An ability to define client objects differently than the server ones,
							and still have seamless persistence.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Generic web service interface that doesn't change when object model
							changes.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>An ability to work in two modes: dedicated session mode or shared
							("chat") mode when multiple remote clients collaboratively work on the
							same data.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Lazy object and collection faulting.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Full context lifecycle</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Queries, expressions, local query caching, paginated queries.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Validation</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Delete Rules</para>
					</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
