<document>
<title>User Guide - Design</title>
<toc name="toc-user-guide" chapter="4. Design"/>
<body>
    <section name="4. Design">
        <subsection name="4.7 Primary Key Generation">
            <p>Depending on the type of persistent objects and the database
            design, primary key values can be handled in a few different ways. 
            A decision to use one or another technique will affect how 
            the mapping is done. Here is a summary of possible scenarious. Each one
            is described below in details.
            </p>
            
             <table>
            <tr>
            	<th></th>
            	<th>PK Has DbAttribute</th>
            	<th>PK Has ObjAttribute</th>
            	<th>PK is a DataObject property</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
            	<td>Meaningful Primary Key</td>
            	<td>Yes</td>
            	<td>Yes</td>
            	<td>Yes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
            	<td>Primary Key Derived From Relationship</td>
            	<td>Yes</td>
            	<td>No</td>
            	<td>No</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
            	<td>Generated Primary Key</td>
            	<td>Yes</td>
            	<td>No</td>
            	<td>No</td>
            </tr>
            </table>
            
            <subsection name="4.7.1 Meaningful Primary Key" anchor="pk-do">            
            <p>DataObjects can provide their own values for the primary key 
            columns. Sometimes this makes sense, for example if a primary
            key column conains meaningful data like a Social Security Number.
            In such cases primary key handling is no different from handling any other
            persistent attributes. Each primary key column (DbAttribute) will
            have an ObjAttribute mapped to it. The Java class implementing DataObject
            will contain a property described by this ObjAttribute. The value
            of this property will be saved to the database.</p>
            </subsection>
            
                   
          	<subsection name="4.7.2 Primary Key Derived From Relationship" anchor="pk-rel">            
            	<p>A primary key column of a table may depend on a primary key 
            	column of another table. This is normally the case with "join"
            	tables used to resolve many-to-many relationships. In such cases 
            	DataObject normally does not contain a property mapped to a PK column.
            	Instead the value is automatically derived by Cayenne
            	from a primary key of a related object using a relationship.
            	</p>
        	</subsection>
        	       
        	<subsection name="4.7.3 Generated Primary Key" anchor="pk-gen">            
            	<p>In most cases, database primary key is a purely relational concept that
            	has no correspondence in the object model. Normally this is a unique
            	sequential number that identifies a row in the database.
            	This means that creating a property in a persistent object that
            	corresponds to a primary key is an artificial step. To avoid doing that
            	Cayenne assigns each object an ObjectId that internally handles the details
            	of primary key handling.</p>
            	
            	<p>When a new DataObject is saved, and its properties and relationships 
            	do not contain primary key values, Cayenne would attempt to
            	automatically generate a key value. Generation mechanism depends
            	on DbAdapter used and can be customized by users by subclassing 
            	one of the included adapters. Current Cayenne adapters use the following mechanisms:
            	
            	<ul>
            		<li>MySQL, PostgreSQL, HSQL Adapter: use select/update from a special AUTO_PK_TABLE lookup table.</li>
            		<li>Oracle Adapter: uses Oracle sequences.</li>
            		<li>DB2 Adapter: uses DB2 sequences.</li>
            		<li>Sybase Adapter: uses a strored procedure tied to AUTO_PK_TABLE lookup table.</li>
            		<li>OpenBase Adapter: uses OpenBase specific NEWID mechanism.</li>
            	</ul>
            	</p>
            	
            	<p>To generate needed database objects for the primary key autogeneration
            	use CayenneModeler and follow the instructions given 
            	<a href="../../modelerguide/common-tasks/pksupport.html">here</a>.</p>
            	
            	<p><i>Note: Cayenne only supports automatic PK generation for a single column per table.</i></p>
            	
            </subsection>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
