<document>
<title>User Guide - Design</title>
<toc name="toc-user-guide" chapter="4. Design"/>
<body>
    <section name="4. Design">
        <subsection name="4.3 Data Objects" anchor="do">
            <p>Cayenne's main function is to provide object-based access
            to relational data sources. DataObjects in Cayenne are fully portable and contain
            only data and business logic. It is a task of the framework to perform operations 
            required to provide objects persistence.</p>
            
            <p>All objects that represent persistent data in Cayenne must implement <a href=
            "../../api/cayenne/org/objectstyle/cayenne/DataObject.html">DataObject</a> interface.
            Default implementation of DataObject is <a href=
            "../../api/cayenne/org/objectstyle/cayenne/CayenneDataObject.html">CayenneDataObject</a>.
            In most cases application classes that are used for data access would extend 
            CayenneDataObject. DataContext provides persistence services to DataObjects:
            </p>
            
            <img src="/images/data-objects.gif" width="420" height="331" alt="Cayenne DataObjects"/> 

            <subsection name="4.3.1 ObjectId">
            	<p>Each object in Cayenne is identified by <a href=
            	"../../api/cayenne/org/objectstyle/cayenne/ObjectId.html">ObjectId</a>. 
            	ObjectId is an abstraction similar to the Primary Key concept in
            	relational databases. Its internal implementation in fact uses 
            	primary key values from the database. Cayenne takes care of creating 
            	and managing ObjectId's. Application developers normally do not 
            	work with ObjectId directly.          		
            	</p>
            	
            	<panel name="Note:">
            	The fact that ObjectIds are opaque has a consequence that
            	primary key columns are normally not included as class properties
            	of DataObjects. From the DataMap perspective, this means that while
            	DbEntities would have attributes that map to primary key columns,
            	ObjEntities will not.
            	</panel>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="4.3.2 Object Persistence States">
            	<p>DataObjects can be in 
            	one of the few persistence states. Transitions between the states occur when
            	user (or Cayenne framework on user's behalf) performs certain operations. 
				The following state diagram lists these transitions for the most common
				scenarious: 
            	</p>
            	
            	<img src="/images/dataobject-state.gif" alt="Cayenne DataObject State Diagram"/> 

            </subsection>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
