<document>
<title>User Guide - Using DataContext</title>
<toc name="toc-user-guide" chapter="6. Using DataContext"/>
<body>   	
    
    <section name="6. Using DataContext">
	<subsection name="6.5 Using DataContextDelegate">
		<p>DataContext supports runtime customization via a <a href=
		"../../api/cayenne/org/objectstyle/cayenne/access/DataContextDelegate.html">DataContextDelegate 
		interface</a>. A user can assign a custom delegate instance to a DataContext
		by calling <code>DataContext.setDelegate(..)</code>. Delegate is optional, and if it is not set, DataContext
		would go on with its default behavior. If a delegate is set, DataContext consults with it at some critical points 
		in the normal flow execution. A delegate can modify the flow, abort an operation, modify objects 
		participating in an operation,  or perform any other tasks it deems necessary. 
		</p>
		
		<p>DataContextDelegate currently has two groups of methods - method to filter select queries, and methods
		to react to external updates of the ObjectStore:</p>
		
		<ul>
			<li><code>public GenericSelectQuery <b>willPerformSelect</b>(DataContext context, GenericSelectQuery query)</code><br/><br/>
			Called from <code>DataContext.performQuery(...)</code> before running any select query, including prefetch queries. Implementation
			has a choice to modify an original query, replace it with alternative one, or return NULL, blocking query execution alltogether.
			<p></p></li>
			
			<li><code>public boolean <b>shouldMergeChanges</b>(DataObject object, DataRow snapshotInStore)</code><br/>
			<code>public boolean <b>shouldProcessDelete</b>(DataObject object)</code><br/>
			<code>public void <b>finishedMergeChanges</b>(DataObject object)</code><br/>
			<code>public void <b>finishedProcessDelete</b>(DataObject object)</code><br/><br/>
			These methods are called by the ObjectStore whenever it performs an update of its state triggered by external
			events. Default ObjectStore behavior is to merge all changes to the existing objects, and change deleted objects state
			to TRANSIENT, removing them from the store. Delegate has an option to abort standard processing by returning "false" from
			"should*" methods.
			<p></p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	
	</subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
