<document>
<title>Cayenne Examples</title>
<toc name="toc-examples"/>
<body>
    <section name="Cayenne Examples">        
	<p>Cayenne examples should be <a href="../download.html">downloaded</a> separately from Cayenne. 
	Examples are normally not tested as thourougly as the core Cayenne code. They are provided mostly 
	for reference and learning purposes.
	</p>
	
	<panel name="Contributing Examples">
	Please contribute your own examples if you think they may be helpful to the new users or 
	demonstrate some unobvious use of Cayenne.
	</panel>
	
	<p>The following examples are currently available:</p>
	
	<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Example</th>
		<th>Description</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="blog-tapestry/index.html">Tapestry Blog</a></td>
		<td>This is a fully functional (though simple) Cayenne/Tapestry blogging application.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="hr-dataview/index.html">HRDataView</a></td>
		<td>Demonstrates how to use Cayenne DataViews to simplify creation of Swing applications
		by taking advantage of rich metadata available via Cayenne.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="data-port/index.html">DataPort</a></td>
		<td>Demonstrates how Cayenne can be used to port relational data from one 
			database to another. It shows the operation of the few internal parts of 
			Cayenne, normally not used in the applications. DataPort also contains a working 
			Ant task, so it has practical value for certain database maintenance tasks.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="ejb-facade/index.html">EJB Facade</a></td>
		<td>Demonstrates deploying Cayenne on JBoss server and accessing it via a SessionBean facade.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="servlet-filter/index.html">Servlet Filter</a></td>
		<td>This is a contribution by Gary Jarrel to provide WebApplicationContextProvider functionality
		(i.e. automatic binding of session DataContext to a thread) via a different servlet container hook - 
		a filter - that is compatible with Servlet specification 2.3. This will be included in the core Cayenne
		in the future release.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td><a href="aggregate-functions/index.html">SQL Aggregate Functions</a></td>
		<td>Demonstrates how to use "derived" DbEntities for SQL aggregate functions, such as
		MIN, MAX, COUNT. With introduction of SQLTemplate this example should be considered 
		deprecated, as derived DbEntities are very limited by nature.
		</td>
	</tr>
	</table>
	
	<subsection name="Installing and Building Examples">
	<p>Most examples are distributed in a source form only, users must compile them
	using Ant buildfiles (build.xml) provided with each example. This is generic instructions for building a given
	example. Some examples may require slightly different steps due to their nature.</p>
	
	<p>Extract contents of cayenne-examples-[version].tar.gz into Cayenne installation directory
	(the location is important for the ant build files to find Cayenne):
	</p>
	<source># cd $CAYENNE_HOME
# gz -dc cayenne-examples-[version].tar.gz | tar xf -</source>

	<p>Go to examples directory and modify "default.properties" file that is shared by all examples. This file
	sets the location of Cayenne installation and JDBC driver.
	</p>

	<p>If a given example contains <code>cayenne.xml</code> file, open it using CayenneModeler, set appropriate 
	connection information for the DataNodes, and generate database schema.</p>

	<p>Build example with ant:</p>
	<source># cd $CAYENNE_HOME/cayenne-examples-[version]/[example-name]
# ant</source>
	</subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
