<document>
<title>CayenneModeler Guide</title>
<toc name="toc-modeler-guide" chapter="4. Common Modeling Tasks"/>
<body>
	<section name="4. Common Modeling Tasks">
	<subsection name="4.7 Setting DataMap Defaults">
 	 	<p>DataMap editing panel allows to define a number of default values for the entities 
		in this map.</p>

<img src="/images/modelerguide/datamap-defaults.jpg" width="512" height="256" border="0" 
        align="middle" alt="DataMap Defaults"/>

		<p>Defaults are stored in the DataMap XML file and used in CayenneModeler 
		to make entity creation/modification easier. The following defaults are supported:</p>

	<ul>
	<li><strong>DB Schema</strong>. 
	Default schema for newly created DbEntities and Procedures. Clicking "Update.." button next
	to default schema will reset the schema of all existing DbEntities and Procedures to match the default.
	<p></p>
	</li>

	<li><strong>Java Package</strong>. 
	Default package for newly created ObjEntities. When specified, newly created ObjEntities will
	be assigned a class name that is a combination of default package and initial entity name. 
	Clicking "Update.." button next
	to default package will reset the package of the existing Java classes in the DataMap.
	<p></p>
	</li>

	<li><strong>DataObject Superclass</strong>. 
	DataObject superclass allows to specify default superclass for the DataObject classes
	mapped via ObjEntities. Clicking "Update.." button next to DataObject superclass field 
	will reset the superclass of all existing Java classes in the DataMap.
	<p></p>
	</li>

	<li><strong>Optimistic Locking</strong>. 
	Default optimistic locking policy for ObjEntities. Clicking "Update.." button next
	to the optimistic locking checkbox will reset the optimistic locking policy of all existing ObjEntities 
	to match the default.
	<p></p>
	</li>
		</ul>

	<panel name="Defaults are ignored in runtime">
	Note that none of the defaults affect entities runtime behavior. For example if a DbEntity "ARTIST"
	has empty schema, and a DataMap defines a default schema to be "SCHEMA1", Cayenne will 
	assume that ARTIST entity does not use schema.
	</panel>

        </subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>





