<document>
	<title>CayenneModeler Guide</title>
	<toc name="toc-modeler-guide" chapter="4. Common Modeling Tasks"/>
	<body>
		<section name="4. Common Modeling Tasks">
			<subsection name="4.3 Reverse Engineer Database">
				<p><strong>Start Reverse Engineering.</strong> To reverse 
					engineer a database you need to select either a DataDomain 
					or one of its children on the project tree. Then select 
					<code>"Tools > Reengineer Database Schema"</code> from the 
					menu. "Connect to Database" dialog will be presented.</p>
				<panel name="Note:">Reverse-engineering behavior is sensitive 
					to the current project tree selection. If you selected a 
					DataDomain or a DataNode, a new DataMap will be created and 
					all reengineered tables will be put in this DataMap. If you 
					had an existing DataMap (or one of its entities) selected 
					when you started reverse engineering, new tables will be 
					merged into the existing DataMap.</panel>
				<p><strong>Configure Database Connection.</strong> "Connect to 
					Database" dialog allows to specify alternative connection 
					parameters. If a DataNode was selected when reverse 
					engineering started, its connection information is shown by 
					default. You can use suggested default connection, select 
					one of the stored local DataSources from "Saved 
					DataSources" dropdown (those can be edited on the spot by 
					clicking "..." button), or type your own info. When desired 
					connection is selected, click "Continue". Cayenne will 
					attempt to connect to the database and if connection is 
					successful, "Select Options" dialog is presented.</p>
				<img src="/images/modelerguide/reengineer-connect.jpg" 
					width="560" height="344" 
					alt="Reengineer Connection Dialog"/>
				<p><strong>Configure Options.</strong> "Select Options" dialog 
					allows to specify what needs to be reverse engineered. If a 
					database supports schemas, one of the listed schemas should 
					be selected. Table and stored procedure patterns allow to 
					control which tables/procedures are included in reverse 
					engineering. Patterns should be in the format used by 
					SQL LIKE clause (e.g. "ABC", "ABC%" or" %" or "A%T", 
					etc.).</p>
				<p>After desired options are selected, click "Continue". 
					Progress dialog will open. It will close automatically when 
					reverse-engineering is done. After that all database tables 
					and stored procedures that matched selected criteria will 
					be added to the DataMap. Default ObjEntity mapping will be 
					created as well.</p>
				<img src="/images/modelerguide/reengineer-schema.jpg" 
					width="560" height="344" alt="Reengineer Select Options"/>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>