<document>
	<title>User Guide - Quick Start</title>
	<toc name="toc-user-guide" chapter="3. Quick Start"/>
	<body>
		<section name="3. Quick Start">
			<subsection name="Common Setup Steps">
				<p>These setup steps are the same for all tutorials in this 
					chapter:</p>
				<p><strong>1. Install Cayenne:</strong><br/> Check <a 
					href="../install/index.html">these</a> and <a 
					href="../install/install.html">these</a> instructions. In 
					particular, JDK 1.4 or newer must be installed.</p>
				<p><strong>2. Get access to a Relational 
					Database:</strong><br/> For instance this can be a shared 
					database running somewhere on the server in your 
					organization. If you don't have access to such database (or 
					don't have permissions to create and drop tables in it), it 
					will probably be simpler if you install a local database on 
					the development machine. All the tutorial SQL scripts were 
					written for MySQL, so installing MySQL should be the 
					simplest option.</p>
				<p><strong>3. Install JDBC Driver:</strong><br/> Install JDBC 
					driver for the database used in step (2). Put the driver 
					jars somewhere in the filesystem. You don't have to add 
					them to CLASSPATH for the CayenneModeler to run, however 
					you may need to do that to run your application.</p>
				<p><strong>4. Start CayenneModeler GUI Application, Configure 
					Driver Settings:</strong><br/> Follow <a 
					href="../../modelerguide/modeler-intro/runmodeler.html">these 
					instructions</a> to start the Modeler.</p>
				<p><strong>5. Configure Driver Settings:</strong><br/> In the 
					Modeler go to <code>"Tools > Preferences > 
					ClassPath"</code> and create an entry or entries for the 
					JDBC driver JAR files installed in the step (3). Once these 
					preferences are saved, they will be used by the Modeler, 
					even after it is restarted.</p>
				<p><strong>6. Configure Preferred DataSources:</strong><br/> Go 
					to <code>"Tools > Preferences > Local DataSources"</code> 
					and configure one or more named DataSources for any 
					databases you might need to access now and in the future. A 
					documentation for this operation can be found <a 
					href="../../modelerguide/preferences/pref-datasource.html">here</a>. 
					<i>This step is optional, however performing it now will 
					speed up any database work that you will do when working on 
					tutorials and with your own application.</i></p>
				<panel name="Note:"> Source code for the tutorials discussed in 
					this chapter is bundled with Cayenne distribution. More 
					advanced Cayenne examples are available as a separate 
					download from the download page. </panel>
				<p>Database schema used in all tutorials in this chapter is 
					shown below:</p>
				<img src="/images/userguide/quickstart-schema.jpg" width="400" 
					height="200" border="0" align="middle" 
					alt="Art Catalog Schema"/>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>