<document>
<title>CayenneModeler Guide</title>
<toc name="toc-modeler-guide" chapter="2. ORM Case Study"/>
<body>
 	 <section name="2. ORM Case Study">
		<p>This chapter shows how ORM (Object Relational Modeling) approach should 
		be chosen based on the project
		requirements and other factors. It contains links to technical aspects of modeling
		that are discussed elsewhere. A few scenarios are shown below that describe 
		the most common cases that a
		development team may encounter on a typical O/R project. Lets assume an 
		imaginary company called "Some Company" that sells services to consumers as its
		main business, but also sells consumer products, and works with business customers.
		There are a number of project teams working on a set of Object/Relational projects.
		</p>
		
		<p><strong>Project 1: Java Interface to an Existing Database</strong></p>
		<p>"Some Company" has a billing system that runs on Sybase database, that
		uses a set of UNIX C++ applications to perform nightly batch jobs and print
		the bills. The project goal is to create a Java client-server Object/Relational system
		that will be used by customer service representatives to provide
		customer support and correct billing errors. Such system must use the existing database
		schema without changing it, but both Swing frontend and Java business layer that performs
		the database access have to be created from scratch.
		</p>
		
		<p><strong>Project 2: New System</strong></p>
		<p>"Some Company" is planning a brand new e-commerce site for its
		web users. Both the database and Java business objects must be designed 
		from scratch as a part of the same project.</p>
		
		<p><strong>Project 3: Converting an Existing Java Business Framework</strong></p>
		<p>Before getting into O/R technology, "Some Company" created a set of Java applications
		for its sales and marketing teams working with business customers. These applications
		use a custom persistence framework based on Data Access Objects (DAO - a term for 
		objects that encapsulate the handcoded SQL for their persistence operations).
		The goal of the project is to convert DAO to Cayenne-based Object/Relational business
		framework, preserving all business rules, and using the existing database.</p>
    </section>
</body>
</document>





